David Steeven Villa Salazar

Computer Science Master Student

PERSONAL PROFILE

Steeven Villa is a computer science master student at UFRGS (Porto Alegre, Brazil) since March 2017, where also takes part of ANNELIDA project lead by PETROBRAS as interface-designer. His research experience is in the field of Physics-based Animation, Virtual reality, Haptic Feedback, 3D and Tangible User Interfaces. He is currently doing an internship at the Rainbow team at Inria (Rennes, France) developing projects related to mid-air and wearable haptics. He received his bachelor degree in Mechatronic Engineering from the Instituto Tecnologico Metropolitano (Medellin, Colombia) in 2016. His principal research interest area is Human-computer interaction.

EDUCATION

MSc. in Computer Science | UFRGS

Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul (Brazil)

Jan. 2017 - In progress

Thesis (Provisory Title): Integrating Physics-based and Data-Driven Methods to Accurately Model

Haptic Textures

Adviser: Prof. Dr. Anderson Maciel

BSc. in Mechatronic Engineering | ITM

Instituto Tecnologico Metropolitano (Colombia)

Aug. 2010 - Dec 2016

Main Research: Computer Simulation of Heat Transfer on Tools Used in Friction Stir Welding

Adviser: Prof. Dr. Edwar A. Torres Lopez

RESEARCH INTEREST

Haptics

Texture Modeling & Rendering | Wearables | Mid-Air Haptics | Multi-sensory perception

Physical-Based Animation

Position-Based Dynamics | Smoothed Particles Hydrodinamics | Deformable Bodies

PARTICIPATION IN RESEARCH PROJECTS

As Master Student

H-Reality

INRIA Rennes | 2019 - Present

Hapto-Graphic Unified Engines for Simulated Medical Interventions

Universidade Federal do rio grande do sul | 2018 - 2019

Desenvolvimento de um robô para operação em dutos de 4" a 10"

Development of a robot for operation in a submarine pipeline of 4" to 10".

Universidade Federal do rio grande do sul | 2017 - 2019

As Bachelor Student

Comparison of methodologies to get phase values in the optical field in lensless digital holographic microscopy

Universidad Nacional de Colombia | 2015 - 2016

Modeling and nonlinear control of fluids dynamics as from an experimental module

Instituto Tecnologico Metropolitano | 2014 - 2015

Fluid-Dynamic computational study of spiral chambers applied to micro-scale hydropower generation.

Instituto Tecnologico Metropolitano | 2014 - 2015

Computer simulation of heat transfer on tools used in friction stir welding

Instituto Tecnologico Metropolitano | 2013 - 2014

Development numerical correlations of heat transfer and pressure drop in twisted tube heat exchanger

Instituto Tecnologico Metropolitano | 2013 - 2014

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Research Intern

INRIA - Rennes-France

Current

Harware Prototyping | Human Perception | Haptics | Wearable Devices

Physical Interface Designer

PETROBRAS - Porto Alegre-Brazil

2017 - Present

Harware Prototyping | Human Factors | Design for Explosive Atmospheres

Cadd Designer & CFD Assistant

COINGAS - Itagui-Colombia

2015 - 2016

Simulation Planing | Numerical model implementation | Petroleum Simulations

UI Designer & Hardware Integrator

PITMMAM - Medellin-Colombia

2015

Hardware Prototyping | UI Planning | Interaction Design | Wireless Communication

Young Researcher

Instituto Tecnologico Metropolitano - Medellin-Colombia

2014 - 2015

Image Processing | Machine Learning | Research | Teaching

LANGUAGES

Spanish (Native) Portuguese (Good) English (Good)

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Languages

C++ C#

Python Processing

Matlab

Digital tools

OpenGL Unity 3D

OpenCV 3D Cadd Design

CFD Simulation FEA Simulation

Physical tools

Arduino Microcontrollers
Raspberry pi Circuit Design
BeagleBone

Haptic and VR Devices

Geomagic Touch Oculus Rift
Ultrahaptics Vicon Tracking

HTC Vive

PUBLICATIONS AND INVITED TALKS

Heat-Based Bidirectional Phase Shifting Simulation using Position-Based Dynamics (Full Paper)

Computers & Graphics 2018.

VILLA, D.; TICONA, J.; TORCHELSEN, R; MACIEL, A.; NEDEL, L.

Ambientes inmersivos: ¿Cómo hacer real lo virtual? (Talk) Immersive environments: How to make the virtual, real? 1er Workshop creciendo en ciencia 2018. (Medellin-Colombia) VILLA, D.

Evaluation of Visual, Auditory and Vibro-Tactile Alerts in Supervised Interfaces (Full Paper)

20TH SYMPÓSIUM ON VIRTUAL AND AUGMENTED REALITY 2018 SOUZA, G.; AMAYA, L.; STEIN, V; VILLA, D.; TICONA, J.; MACIEL, A.; NEDEL, L.

3DAthlon: 3D Gestural Interfaces to Support a 3-Stage Contest in VR (Short Paper)

IEEE Conference on Virtual Reality and 3D User Interfaces 2018.

GRANDI, JJ; DEBARBA, H; FRANZ, J; OLIVEIRA, V; TICONA, A; SOUZA, G; BERTI, I; VILLA, D; NEDEL, L; MACIEL, A.

Computer Simulation of Heat Transfer on Tools Used in Friction Stir Welding. (Full Paper - Spanish)

Revista UIS Ingenierias (2015): vol. 14, no 2, p.p. 19-26.

VILLA, D.; HINCAPIE, D. y TORRES, E.

PARTICIPATION IN STUDENT CHALLENGES

UltraMotion | UTRAHAPTICS Challenge

VILLA, D.; OLIVEIRA, V.| EUROHAPTICS 2018 | Pisa, Italia | Finalist

3DAthlon | 3DUI Contest

CG-UFRGS Team | IEEE 3DUI | Reutlingen, Germany | Finalist

AWARDS

RESOLUCION N348 POR MEDIO DE LA CUAL SE CONCEDE MENCION AL MERITO POR ACTIVIDADES DE INVESTIGACION A UNOS ALUMNOS DE LA FACULTAD DE INGENIERIAS (Research Award)

ITM (Colombia) | 2014